<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Highlights on Research Group of Quantum Network, USTC</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/</link><description>Recent content in Highlights on Research Group of Quantum Network, USTC</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 20:40:25 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2024 National College Student Information Security Contest</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/ciscn_2024/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 19:30:18 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/ciscn_2024/</guid><description>&lt;p>On August 14, 2024, the 17th National College Student Information Security Contest Finals successfully concluded at the Taicang Smart Port Campus of Northwestern Polytechnical University. The team of undergraduate students from our laboratory won the second prize with their project &amp;ldquo;IPSec VPN Data Security Transmission Platform Integrated with Quantum Key&amp;rdquo;, supervised by Associate Researcher Jian Li.&lt;/p>
&lt;div align="center">
 &lt;img src="https://qnlab-ustc.com/images/ciscn_2024_2.png" width="800px" />
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>The project aims to integrate quantum key into the traditional IPSec protocol, achieving quantum-resistant security features while maintaining compatibility. To address high-security demands from users, the team introducs the One-Time Pad algorithm. To solve the efficiency issue caused by the low key supply rate in the One-Time Pad mode, the team designs a dynamic key update algorithm to balance security and transmission efficiency. Additionally, to tackle the problems of decreased long-term storage security and difficult key synchronization, the team incorporats a key management mechanism to securely store and synchronize keys generated by QKD (Quantum Key Distribution). Through these designs, the team builds an IPSec VPN data security transmission platform integrated with quantum keys, based on actual QKD devices, and developed a GUI for user convenience.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Building a Large-Scale and Wide-Area Quantum Internet Based on an OSI-Alike Model</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/china-communication/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/china-communication/</guid><description>&lt;p>The theory and experiment of quantum information have been studied extensively in recent years, and the feasibility of quantum communication has been proved. Although the fundamental technology is not yet mature, research on quantum internet should be conducted. To implement quantum internet, an architecture that describes how quantum nodes are linked to form networks and how protocol functions are vertically composed need to be developed urgently. In this paper, we present a novel design of a cluster-based structure to describe how quantum nodes are interconnected, and how the structure can improve the performance of qubit transmission and reduce the network complexity. The idea of the quantum local area network (QLAN) is proposed as an essential component of the quantum internet. Besides, each quantum repeater links to neighboring repeaters to form a core network, and multiple QLANs are connected through the core network. The core network can be grouped into different hierarchical quantum repeater networks according to needed service requirements. For the sake of interoperability and fast prototyping, we adopt the idea of OSI layering model of the current Internet in the design of quantum internet. Finally, we elaborate on the composition of quantum nodes and the realization of end-to-end communication.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Entanglement-Assisted Quantum Networks: Mechanics, Enabling Technologies, Challenges, and Research Directions</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/ieee_commu_sur_tur/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/ieee_commu_sur_tur/</guid><description>&lt;p>Quantum applications offer significant advantages over their classical counterparts primarily due to the fundamental principles of quantum mechanics, especially quantum entanglement. To harness the full potential and broaden the scope of quantum applications, it becomes imperative to establish entanglement-assisted quantum networks by connecting multiple quantum nodes through physical channels. Quantum networks have shown promise in terms of improving the overall functional benefits of the Internet and enabling applications with no counterpart in the classical world, which is a breakthrough technology towards the unimaginable future. However, entanglement-assisted quantum networks differ fundamentally from classical networks, encompassing various aspects including physical resources and top-level applications. Therefore, it is crucial to undertake fundamental yet essential endeavors in order to pave the way for building entanglement-assisted quantum networks.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>REDP: Reliable Entanglement Distribution Protocol Design for Large-scale Quantum Networks</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/redp-jsac/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/redp-jsac/</guid><description>&lt;p>Remote entanglement distribution in an efficient and reliable manner, especially in the context of a largescale quantum network with multiple requests, remains an unsolved challenge. The key difficulties lie in achieving spontaneous and precise control over the entanglement distribution procedure, as multiple nodes need to reach a consensus on how to perform it. From the network aspect, allocating link-layer entangled pairs as resources to achieve high efficiency is also challenging. To address these issues, we propose a decentralized Reliable Entanglement Distribution Protocol (REDP) for large-scale networks. The protocol operates in a Forward-Backward Propagation (FBP) manner, where consensus is reached hop-by-hop and disseminated to all nodes on the path. We further use probabilistic analysis and quasi-static modeling to seek the fairness and efficiency of the network based on the above transmission model. Accordingly, we introduce a Source Window Strategy (SWS) and an Entanglement Allocation Strategy (EAS) to assign sending windows and allocate resources for multiple requests, ensuring a high level of fairness and efficiency from a network perspective. Through systematic simulations involving both classical and quantum communication protocols, we demonstrate that REDP outperforms existing approaches in terms of fairness, throughput, and fidelity performance.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SimQN: a Network-layer Simulator for the Quantum Network Investigation</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/simqn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 11:39:58 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/simqn/</guid><description>&lt;script>
window.location.href = "/projects/simqn";
&lt;/script></description></item></channel></rss>