<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Highlights on Research Group of Quantum Network, USTC</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/</link><description>Recent content in Highlights on Research Group of Quantum Network, USTC</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>REDP: Reliable Entanglement Distribution Protocol Design for Large-scale Quantum Networks</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/redp-jsac/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/redp-jsac/</guid><description>Remote entanglement distribution in an efficient and reliable manner, especially in the context of a largescale quantum network with multiple requests, remains an unsolved challenge. The key difficulties lie in achieving spontaneous and precise control over the entanglement distribution procedure, as multiple nodes need to reach a consensus on how to perform it. From the network aspect, allocating link-layer entangled pairs as resources to achieve high efficiency is also challenging. To address these issues, we propose a decentralized Reliable Entanglement Distribution Protocol (REDP) for large-scale networks.</description></item><item><title>SimQN: a Network-layer Simulator for the Quantum Network Investigation</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/simqn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 11:39:58 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/simqn/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Building a Large-Scale and Wide-Area Quantum Internet Based on an OSI-Alike Model</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/china-communication/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/china-communication/</guid><description>The theory and experiment of quantum information have been studied extensively in recent years, and the feasibility of quantum communication has been proved. Although the fundamental technology is not yet mature, research on quantum internet should be conducted. To implement quantum internet, an architecture that describes how quantum nodes are linked to form networks and how protocol functions are vertically composed need to be developed urgently. In this paper, we present a novel design of a cluster-based structure to describe how quantum nodes are interconnected, and how the structure can improve the performance of qubit transmission and reduce the network complexity.</description></item><item><title>Entanglement-Assisted Quantum Networks: Mechanics, Enabling Technologies, Challenges, and Research Directions</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/ieee_commu_sur_tur/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/ieee_commu_sur_tur/</guid><description>Quantum applications offer significant advantages over their classical counterparts primarily due to the fundamental principles of quantum mechanics, especially quantum entanglement. To harness the full potential and broaden the scope of quantum applications, it becomes imperative to establish entanglement-assisted quantum networks by connecting multiple quantum nodes through physical channels. Quantum networks have shown promise in terms of improving the overall functional benefits of the Internet and enabling applications with no counterpart in the classical world, which is a breakthrough technology towards the unimaginable future.</description></item></channel></rss>