<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research Group of Quantum Network, USTC</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/</link><description>Recent content on Research Group of Quantum Network, USTC</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 11:39:58 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qnlab-ustc.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SimQN: a Network-layer Simulator for the Quantum Network Investigation</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/simqn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 11:39:58 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/simqn/</guid><description/></item><item><title>SimQN: a Network-layer Simulator for the Quantum Network Investigation</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/projects/simqn/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 13:40:06 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/projects/simqn/</guid><description>Welcome to SimQN&amp;rsquo;s documentation. SimQN is a discrete-event based network simulation platform for quantum networks. SimQN enables large-scale investigations, including QKD protocols, entanglement distributions protocols, and routing algorithms, resource allocation schemas in quantum networks. For example, users can use SimQN to design routing algorithms for better QKD performance. For more information, please refer to the Documents.
SimQN is a Python3 library for quantum networking simulation. It is designed to be general propose.</description></item><item><title>About Us</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/about/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 13:27:40 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/about/</guid><description>To the future of quantum era Nowadays, we are on the cusp of a new age of technology that promises to revolutionize the way we compute, communicate, and secure information. Quantum mechanics, which describes the behavior of particles at the subatomic level, has long been recognized as a powerful tool for information processing. The advancements of quantum mechanics have the potential to solve problems that were previously impossible to solve with classical networks and computers, to provide unprecedented levels of security for our communications, and to create entirely new industries and fields of study.</description></item><item><title>Building a Large-Scale and Wide-Area Quantum Internet Based on an OSI-Alike Model</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/china-communication/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/china-communication/</guid><description>The theory and experiment of quantum information have been studied extensively in recent years, and the feasibility of quantum communication has been proved. Although the fundamental technology is not yet mature, research on quantum internet should be conducted. To implement quantum internet, an architecture that describes how quantum nodes are linked to form networks and how protocol functions are vertically composed need to be developed urgently. In this paper, we present a novel design of a cluster-based structure to describe how quantum nodes are interconnected, and how the structure can improve the performance of qubit transmission and reduce the network complexity.</description></item><item><title>Entanglement-Assisted Quantum Networks: Mechanics, Enabling Technologies, Challenges, and Research Directions</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/ieee_commu_sur_tur/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/ieee_commu_sur_tur/</guid><description>Quantum applications offer significant advantages over their classical counterparts primarily due to the fundamental principles of quantum mechanics, especially quantum entanglement. To harness the full potential and broaden the scope of quantum applications, it becomes imperative to establish entanglement-assisted quantum networks by connecting multiple quantum nodes through physical channels. Quantum networks have shown promise in terms of improving the overall functional benefits of the Internet and enabling applications with no counterpart in the classical world, which is a breakthrough technology towards the unimaginable future.</description></item><item><title>News</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/news/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/news/</guid><description>2023.9, our paper &amp;ldquo;A Connectionless Entanglement Distribution Protocol Design in Quantum Networks&amp;rdquo; is accepted by IEEE Network!
2023.7, our paper &amp;ldquo;An Efficient Scheduling Scheme of Swapping and Purification Operations for End-to-End Entanglement Distribution in Quantum Networks&amp;rdquo; is accepted by IEEE Transactions on Network Science and Engineering!
2023.7, our paper &amp;ldquo;Efficient Remote Entanglement Distribution in Quantum Networks: A Segment-based Method&amp;rdquo; is accepted by IEEE Transactions on Network and Service Management!</description></item><item><title>Our Team</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/team/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/team/</guid><description>Scientific Counselor Jun Lu Professor
Academician of Chinese Academy of Engineering
Qibin Sun Professor
IEEE Fellow
Nenghai Yu Professor
Executive Dean of the School of Cyber Security, USTC
Faculty Kaiping Xue Professor
E-mail
Homepage Jian Li Research Associate
E-mail
Homepage Zhonghui Li Post-Doc
E-mail
Homepage Ph.D Students Zhaoying Wang E-mail
Lutong Chen E-mail
Yuxin Chen E-mail
Master Students Jiesheng Tan E-mail
Puli Li E-mail
Peng Zheng E-mail
Zirui Xiao E-mail</description></item><item><title>Publications</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/publication/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/publication/</guid><description>Preprints arXiv
2023 A Connectionless Entanglement Distribution Protocol Design in Quantum Networks
Zirui Xiao, Jian Li*, Kaiping Xue, Zhonghui Li, Nenghai Yu, Qibin Sun, Jun Lu
IEEE Network, Accepted.
An Efficient Scheduling Scheme of Swapping and Purification Operations for End-to-End Entanglement Distribution in Quantum Networks
Zhaoying Wang, Jian Li*, Kaiping Xue*, David S. L. Wei, Ruidong Li, Nenghai Yu, Qibin Sun, Jun Lu
IEEE Transactions on Network Science and Engineering, (Early Access).</description></item></channel></rss>