<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Group of Quantum Network, USTC</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/</link><description>Recent content on Group of Quantum Network, USTC</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 11:39:58 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://qnlab-ustc.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SimQN: a Network-layer Simulator for the Quantum Network Investigation</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/simqn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 11:39:58 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/simqn/</guid><description/></item><item><title>News</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/news/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 11:23:39 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/news/</guid><description>新闻页面（英文）</description></item><item><title>SimQN: a Network-layer Simulator for the Quantum Network Investigation</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/projects/simqn/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 13:40:06 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/projects/simqn/</guid><description>Welcome to SimQN&amp;rsquo;s documentation. SimQN is a discrete-event based network simulation platform for quantum networks. SimQN enables large-scale investigations, including QKD protocols, entanglement distributions protocols, and routing algorithms, resource allocation schemas in quantum networks. For example, users can use SimQN to design routing algorithms for better QKD performance. For more information, please refer to the Documents.
SimQN is a Python3 library for quantum networking simulation. It is designed to be general propose.</description></item><item><title>Publications</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/publication/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 13:32:11 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/publication/</guid><description>Preprints arXiv
2022 An Asynchronous Entanglement Distribution Protocol for Quantum Networks
Zhaoying Wang; Jian Li; Kaiping Xue; Shaoyin Cheng; Nenghai Yu; Qibin Sun; Jun Lu
IEEE Network,Volume: 36, Issue: 5
Online - PDF
A Heuristic Remote Entanglement Distribution Algorithm on Memory-Limited Quantum Paths
Lutong Chen; Kaiping Xue; Jian Li; Nenghai Yu; Ruidong Li; Jianqing Liu; Qibin Sun; Jun Lu
IEEE Transactions on Communications, Volume: 70, Issue: 11
Online - PDF</description></item><item><title>About Us</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/about/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 13:27:40 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/about/</guid><description>To the future of quantum era</description></item><item><title>Our Team</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/team/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 13:25:55 +0800</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/team/</guid><description>People Staff Lu Jun Nenghai Yu Kaiping Xue kpxue AT ustc.edu.cn
Kaiping Xue lijian9 AT ustc.edu.cn
Ph.D Student Zhonghui Li
e-mail: @mail.ustc.edu.cn
Zhaoying Wang
e-mail: @mail.ustc.edu.cn
Lutong Chen
e-mail: @mail.ustc.edu.cn
Master Student Mingjun Wang
e-mail: @mail.ustc.edu.cn
Peng Zheng
e-mail: @mail.ustc.edu.cn
Zirui Xiao
e-mail: @mail.ustc.edu.cn</description></item><item><title>Building a Large-Scale and Wide-Area Quantum Internet Based on an OSI-Alike Model</title><link>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/china-communication/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://qnlab-ustc.com/highlights/china-communication/</guid><description>The theory and experiment of quantum information have been studied extensively in recent years, and the feasibility of quantum communication has been proved. Although the fundamental technology is not yet mature, research on quantum internet should be conducted. To implement quantum internet, an architecture that describes how quantum nodes are linked to form networks and how protocol functions are vertically composed need to be developed urgently. In this paper, we present a novel design of a cluster-based structure to describe how quantum nodes are interconnected, and how the structure can improve the performance of qubit transmission and reduce the network complexity.</description></item></channel></rss>